soft engineering radio episode 110 rolls
in software engineering part 1 this is
software engineering radio the podcast
for professional developers on the web
at s e - radio dotnet se radio prints
irrelevant and detailed discussions and
interviews on soft engineering topics
every 10 days thanks to our audience and
the partners listed on our website for
supporting the pod
[Music]
okay then welcome listeners to another
episode of software engineering radio in
this episode we're going to talk about
roles in software engineering and also
skills and competencies so what people
are required to be able to do for
certain roles Michael is on the other
end of the wire hello Michael
hello Marcus so I'm going to play the
the interviewer so Michael is going to
be the person who is going to do most of
the of the important talking so Michael
I guess before we actually start and
talk about the specific roles why don't
you give us a little bit of a background
why you came up with this episode why
you want to talk about it and you know
what are some of the backgrounds okay so
first hello listeners this episode is
something I have been looking for very
much and the reason we do this episode
on software engineering roles on roles
in the in that environment is because we
got quite a few times asked by you
listeners to do an episode and on those
topics and second I think it's it's
quite exciting to discuss this topic
with with colleagues with peers and what
I realized over over time that mmm I
believe I I was able to factor out some
common understanding of the roles in in
our discipline and so it should serve as
a guidance to two newbies two juniors on
what kind of role understanding what
kind of software engineering chops are
out there and of course from a
background it's more on a corporate
level than then on a two or three person
shop also what we do how we start off is
with the roles we we focus more on a
classical separation or
after work we will get to a separation
how it will look like and then HL in an
scrum wait at the end of the episode or
maybe it's already the next episode
depending on the length how long we we
take for it yeah so yeah of course it's
it's biased by personal experience but I
also try to validate it and and
cross-check it with with colleagues and
peers as I said
yeah and and I think it's important to
mention also that that these are roles
that means it's not necessarily
different people one role can be played
by several people and of course also one
person can play several roles right at
least for some of the combinations is
purely about roles and that you would
typically start with with one person but
there is no no problem in in certain
environments that you associate several
roles with one person it will be
difficult and a challenge for for this
person to know when to play which hat
but besides that there is generally no
no disallowance or something that
nothing that says that you can't do that
right okay so during this episode there
will be a couple of terms that that show
up over and over again there are skills
experiences competencies do you want to
define those or at least give people an
X you know an understanding of what what
the difference between those terms is
and why you distinguish them yeah we
still we mean mainly the soft skills
such as communication creativity
analysis skills or the ability to
abstract ability to organize things
correctly or also for the leading
positions like things like assertiveness
for competencies this includes things
like technologies processes and
methodologies things that you can learn
by reading a book and and gain
experience on it we also have an
unfeeling on how much experience you
should have in a certain technology or
how much experience you should have on
the top in a certain role but we don't
stress that point because that is really
something which depends heavily on the
person that lists this role the third
thing that is for me quite exciting and
maybe maybe the most important thing is
the mindset like what is your motor
motto or what is your motivation every
day why do you do all that what's the
thing that drives you yeah what what
drives you every day what drives in
every conversation what drives you to do
this job what is what is crucial to this
role and so all the skills and
competencies do not really matter when
the mindset is the wrong one for this
kind of yeah where would you put things
like the ability to abstract to cope
with complexity the ability to simplify
to see the essence in something is that
is that a competencies that a skill is
that almost a soft skill where will you
put those because I find that these are
important the ability to abstract this
is definite
soft skill I would say and to cope with
complexity is like the same thing but
from a different view yeah
you deal typically with complexity in
our discipline by abstracting away by
finding models by Rabia by abstraction
you find some some simplicity and to to
simplify things to really aim mmm at
bracket ISM I would call this is my
monster something like a mindset thing
the the pragmatism I I have in
everything I I do okay so I guess that's
enough for the you know the what do you
say epilogue no prologue father for the
stuff in the beginning front matter as
they call it in book publishing so let's
look at at our at our various roles and
maybe start off with looking at typical
tracks or typical different kinds of
software engineering careers I guess you
always start off as a junior developer
and then you can you know go in
different directions right right so in
in software engineering you typically
would start really with getting your
hands dirty I I said I say yeah and that
is typically as a as a junior developer
develop code program but also care about
all the other software engineering
topics don't don't I think only in the
code think also about about the sign and
and so when I say developer it's really
not programmer I say it's much more
junior software engineer that that
focuses on developing software and from
that on you you typically then get into
a more senior role we call it here in
this episode senior developer or
Software Architect or tester or team
lead or Project Lead and we we have
grouped those more advanced most senior
roles
behind us junior developer in inner
career because there is of course some
personal opinion I believe being a
Project Lead being a good architect
being a good tester you must have
developed at one time code on your own
and yeah this is not to say that an
architect later than always should have
contact with with the code but I know
that it's hard if you are in a large
organization to stay in touch with the
code I I know that challenge now yeah
right so so there is no that you have
nothing to do in software engineering if
you didn't ever code
I guess that's maybe a little bit
provocative but I would say that's the
same thing and I know that I'm in
conflict with some of the guys out there
to truly lead and manage the software
project you you should have had your you
should have gotten your hands dirty once
right host
there is also a more it's a requirements
product business focused track where
people start off as a requirements
analyst or requirements engineer right
right and for requirements engineering
and product management and software
there is typically the entry role as in
requirements analyst as in requirements
engineer where you would analyze the
domain requirements and then continue
off as for example as a product manager
now there's also an interesting
discussion I regularly have and we're
have no concerns is whether a product
manager should have a software developer
background or not run is if he
understands too much of the technology
it's hard for him to play and and play
so lead a customer voice like what a
customer likes to do and typically the
customer doesn't care how its
implemented inside but much more on the
usability on on the features right and
so this is this is something that I had
no final conclusion on what but we get
to that
okay there are also other roles or yeah
you know the guy who writes
documentation a UI design or usability
person and also some kind of database
admin or app server ESP admin would you
would you consider those qualities
things just qualifications of a
developer or are these separate roles
with separate career paths mm-hmm I mean
I don't see them so closely related to
the software development track like you
can be a good administrator without
having having written large applications
when you were familiar with a scripting
language
I guess you you can already be an
excellent administrator or on UI
designer this is also something should
you know the implementation technology I
guess you should know the constraints
but mmm do you should you have
necessarily programmed I don't know I I
also there I have no final conclusion
writing it's I think it's good to have
it done once to know the limitations but
you can also be a good UI designer I
guess without that knowledge
documentation writer of course
understanding how a software engineer
things helps to write a documentation
for those guys for for the products they
create to better understand them but I
also have very good examples for example
markers we know Steve Ricker be from Y
night I don't know whether he programmed
in the past but he has a very good
understanding of what we talk about in
our software books yeah actually I'm
well I'm we might get him on the show at
some point but just to clarify another
thing I think we distinguish here
between a documentation writer who
writes like user documentation and you
know the developer who writes technical
documentation about what he just
implemented or describing the
architecture I guess describing
architecture design implementation is
somebody everybody should be able to do
so some writing skills are really useful
for a software developer but we see the
role of actually writing and you
documentation that we see as a separate
thing this
okay so just though people don't say you
who you know I don't need to be able to
write as a software developer and I
guess that's not at all what we want to
say no this is what we also mean with
communication skills there are of course
two oral communication skills but the
written ones are I would guess as
important and yes they are also
important in hol projects yes how to
communicate how to present how to
convince others I mean if you're
interested in that stuff go to the
manager tools podcast I guess if there
is a lot of stuff on that okay so let's
start off with the junior June junior
developer high a not able to talk today
what are some of the skills that that
the junior developer has to have
basically when when he comes from
university to a software shop okay let
me first start off with a little brief
disclaimer anode this is when we talk
about a junior developer this is really
the base level and all the skills we
mentioned and and the mindset thing is
also important for for more senior roles
later and that we add so that we
basically inherit all the skills into
the later roles
I would start off with organizing things
as a as a junior developer you should be
able to organize and structure your
daily work to be able to structure your
design choices to basically prepare you
work elaborate on the requirements
understand the requirements and come up
with design solution structure rate as
design solutions and and find solutions
in an in a structured approach so when I
say structured I think the point is that
you should be able to explain somebody
else what your thoughts were and how you
came to that solution so it's not about
drawing UML diagrams or structured
software development or any of that no I
mean this this might help to draw on UML
I know about UML but in generally use
your feet use your arms fingers your
voice your writing to express yourself
and then we are already with the
communication skills and able to express
your ideas to be able to write
documentation to write down your design
reasoning and a design decision this is
something I want to emphasize again
that's pretty important and later to
know why the solution now looks like
that and didn't become another solution
have you heard about the book the back
of the napkin I heard about it but never
never read it I mean the process of
reading it and it's about visual
communication without you know without
PowerPoint just drawing a bunch of
pictures basically it actually looks
like a really interesting way to
communicate things just as a as a side
we'll probably put it in the show notes
since you talked about communication
here okay next one is analyzer skills
like really to be to be able and digging
deep into the problem find abstractions
develop solutions for specific focus
given problems so here my expectation is
not to be able to
hmm solve the world problem but being
being given a certain task an area in
the architecture a certain functionality
developed solutions for it and I like
then also the ratings like what is the
consequence of the solution what would
be the consequence of another solution
what would be the benefit what is the
trade-off that I that I do here get it
reviewed by and by your Software
Architect or senior developer that is
coaching you and and then start off
implementing it so to me this sounds
like you're referring to some of our
common background which is patterns so
would you say that being able to to
write things down or communicate things
using the pattern form where all those
things you know benefits trade-offs
disadvantages advantages are are
mentioned do you think that's a useful
thinking and communication template
markers of course softball question yeah
no writing honestly really helps you to
sharpen your analyzes and your
communication skills right because with
the feedback you get and writers
workshops by by having your patterns
your your proto patterns reviewed by
some peers by experienced guys by a blob
shepherd for example you will get
valuable feedback and they will
challenge you and will you will really
improve in your writing but also in your
thinking and your and your ability to
extract and find the the more general
issues the more general problem and
solution for your concrete solution you
also manage creativity as one of the
skills right creativity this is
something that I really expect from a
junior developer
well bebe just curious curious be
creative about finding solutions when
you're a while and a job I feel it's at
one point you tend to lose your
creativity because you did a solution 10
times and you know it vertie 10 times
that way you follow that pattern and you
don't challenge it anymore and so the
tuners often come around and tried
totally different ways sometimes they
succeed sometimes they fail but when
they succeed it's it's really a valuable
and important contribution to the
project so I like the reactivity that
those join yourself think unconventional
right out out out of the outside the
boxing thank you right okay so let's
look at some of the competencies I guess
the person should be a software engineer
by education I hope I think this is
again there's a certain mindset of me
and and some experience careful because
I'm not a software engineer by education
right just be careful you one of the
most valuable and most honored software
engineers is having having a software
engineering background on from an
education from University from from a
computer science studies or from other
studies where you learned about software
engineering what it means what what
testing is what bought project
management is having heard all the terms
once and broadly understanding the field
helps helps me a lot hiring hiring you
as a junior developer right and having
to start off on the green field and just
having some programming knowledge is is
okay but
there's done lots of work to be done and
thanks to to experience till till you
really grasp the whole field and and the
consequences of what you're doing I
think it's worth restating that you
don't say you need an education in
computer science right you say software
engineering so so you do distinguish
between computer science and software
engineering right right and in computer
science I knows computer scientists who
had never a lecture in software
engineering and I've also heard that
there are some computer science guys who
never programmed and so just this is
amazingly it's amazing but it's possible
yes No
then what what else should this should
junior developer know about this is some
concrete technology some concrete
programming languages I don't I don't
say it it needs to be one or two or
three it needs to be an interest and
programming language and of course
proficient in at least one or two the
ones that you typically have in your
project you you would hire junior-m more
easily and more probably when he has
some some language skills already but
that is not a key part there there are
more important things as I said this is
the mindset but I said there was there
was a blick he post by Martin Fowler a
while ago where he said that it is more
important that the well I'm paraphrasing
that the mindset is right you can teach
the guy the language of the technology
but you cannot change his mind so just
hire four mindset and skills not four
specific technologies exactly that's a
good way to put it now next is testing
here it really helps again a lot when
when the junior knows already about
testing knows why he does the unit
testing and respects that testing is not
something purely tedious but it it saves
him from over hours at the end of the
day yeah and that that really helps to
ensure quality and that's just the way
we do it today and programming without
testing is I don't know what to say is
hacking or yes it's it's just without
you know developing code without the
safety net and and and just to be clear
again what you talk about is developer
tests or unit tests you don't talk about
system tests and integration testing
that's what you have two separate tests
the roles right yes okay the domain
knowledge this is also same thing a nice
to have but you must be but as soon as
you are with a company for a while
you're expected to understand the domain
in the range where you need to under
understand it you don't need to have the
full understanding on the whole medical
and postal automation of whatever domain
but understand the problems sufficiently
the consequences and the constraints to
find good solutions of to your problems
at hand I guess also that this is
somewhat specific to your let's say
product development background because
if you're hiring a junior for us let's
say project house right then then there
is there isn't usually much specific
domain knowledge because you might do a
project in this domain today and then
another domain tomorrow that's true yeah
yeah okay so much for the competencies I
guess yeah mindset mindset for me the
key part and this is again something
that if that is not available I would
have really problems hiring and hiring
the junior this is for me the first
thing is pragmatism to the simplest
thing that could possibly work is how XP
states it come back and I really love
this the statement and
it can help you everyday and save your
company lots of money when you adhere to
it and that's the reason my I I like the
statement via like pragmatism because
solutions to you of what you develop it
gets easily so complex and it's so hard
to then reduce this complexity again and
and very often in most cases it's not
reduced which is unfortunate for the
project and costly for the company so
having developers that focus on that on
the elementary things is is quite
essential now second is curiosity be
curious be be eager to learn to
constantly learn new things new
programming languages new methodologies
new concepts new technologies constantly
expand your knowledge because our area
is our our discipline is moving so fast
yeah happy to really up-to-date right
okay so I think to to distinguish the
the the software developer or junior
developer from some of the most senior
roles I think one way of looking at it
is that the junior developer typically
looks at a or works in a relatively
small problem area something focused
something specific
whereas architects are responsible for
the bigger picture right is that is that
a fair assessment okay so then let's
let's move on I guess to the senior
developer right I guess that the first
question is how do you become one you
start as a junior and then how do you
become senior is it purely a question of
being in the company for long enough no
it's not a matter of how long you stayed
with the company hopefully not
it's about your impact in the project in
the in the solution it's about your
background it's about your ability to
lead it's about your ability to deal
with complexity and so then so
this basically skills with the skills
yes sir okay so let's let's look at the
skills of a senior develop we already
mentioned leadership this is the first
girl you should be able to coach and
lead a group of other software
developers especially coach to meurs on
the top and so for this it's it's a
different role that that you act and you
have suddenly responsibility not only
for your own results but also for the
results and the sign and the also the
yeah it's it's a result of a whole group
of people which is very different and
will be a change a strong change in your
role and your acting and how you how you
have to work daily right so but he still
works with code right he's not lying to
the horsemeat code with code yes okay
but the second is the ability to
abstract ability to keep him keep the
overview the ability to see the bigger
picture and find solutions in larger
context be able to understand the
complete solution the complete workflow
the complete structure see yeah I I put
it the best ways you see the bigger
world a bigger picture now and in all
the problems I have a better
understanding my thorough understanding
of the context mm-hmm and if it's about
leading a bunch of other developers than
I guess you become something of a
communication harp also so you you have
to communicate between your group of
folks and also from your group of folks
to to to higher-ups into the
organization right right here I really
expect for example as a manager that the
senior developer can explain things to
me in a in a language and using a
terminology that well he adapts to what
I are able to to what I'm able to
understand with my background
so he goes really yes this kind of
background and so I can talk about
classes and methods and and unit tests
or whatever terminology I need to
abstract away my nitty-gritty details
and and tell him the the status project
status problem or demand in in a
suitable way and and and who are you I
mean who is the senior develop
communicating tooth communicating to
management to project lead to the team
lead to other folks maybe also with with
a customer when the customer wants to
get a demo and is he gets presented a
current status he might ask some
questions some technical questions on
usability or so yeah you should be able
to explain the customer and give him a
good answer
competencies competencies and knowledge
like here it's really important then to
understand how to do large-scale design
so here not only to sign patterns but
also architectural patterns and and
patterns in a general sense Arum partner
mmm be so structured that you can easily
guide others in finding their solutions
and encourage them and in them at the
more general aspects of what they
currently try to solve right
your brother yeah next is his process
knowledge know how to optimize your
development process so very often you as
a developer get into an organization
into a project and start off developing
and using the existing tooling the
existing processes and hear from a
senior I expect that he challenges this
tooling constantly and tries to to find
improvements and but this to find the
improvements to know how how to optimize
his work it's it's important to
understand the processes to have having
seen several kind of implementations of
process implementations Rylan I have a
feeling for it and help to improve the
processes around him okay and of course
as we mentioned before plus all the
stuff the junior developer does and
knows and has skills and and
competencies you don't forget that as
you become a more senior person
obviously yes so mindset mindset here I
I would put it that way be a role model
for junior developers somebody where
every junior looks up to and says well I
want to be one day that kind of guy or
girl sorry
so yeah basically this is for me the
typical software engineer where I say
with without any specializations the
senior developer can also deal with
configuration management issues there
helps to improve the process keeps the
project running they are the heart of
the project and without having a senior
or several seniors in your project you
typically won't start do you have any
idea I mean you mentioned before but do
you have any idea how many years roughly
a junior has to spend until it becomes a
senior or is it absolutely pointless to
try to come up with numbers because it's
so different for each person
now I have some numbers and you might
not necessarily agree your listeners but
I would say three to five years at least
after one year of being a junior you
won't
having seen really all the consequences
of what you developed so projects are
typically longer and it needs it takes
more time till you really face the
consequences of of everything like of
having set up the wrong and integration
strategy having chosen the wrong
architecture having chosen the wrong
technology or just having also enjoying
what what you did on the assitive site
like earning all the all the credits and
this takes years
I would guess till you have seen two
three projects preferably in different
technologies and then you have
sufficient experience and and can
abstract the way the the the single
coincidences and write see the bigger
patterns and in your behavior
you mentioned the term pattern again
last thing here if you talk about the
guy you know coaching and leading a
group of juniors then of course this is
not meant to mean that those are his
official subordinates he's not their
boss he has now in German personal foul
on bottom right right so he has no
direct reports right functionally okay
so just to clarify that okay so the next
step up the ladder if you wish is the
software architect also called the
technical lead you calling him
technically probably has the advantage
you don't have to use this term
architect which is somehow has a bad
taste in some communities yeah the role
or the name architect this is quite over
and miss you met for many often and so I
feel that the term technical eat
expresses it more more cleanly more
without any bias so what's the what's
the responsibility of that person how is
that how is he has his activities how is
his role different from the senior
developer we had before
for the software architect I he I feel
that he as as I mentioned with the term
technical lead
he leads the broad check technically and
for for leading the project I think it's
important first that you communicate to
all stakeholders the to really ensure
the information flow in your
organization next to coach others to
adhere to best design practices next is
to ensure the consistency mm-hmm that's
the big picture thing rhynocs a
consistency yeah in my experience
consistency is best achieved by having
reviews and I say reviews are not really
designing things by yourself because in
large organizations you you won't be
able to scale up and solve all the
design decisions yourself you you have
to rely on the individual design choices
of everybody in the organization of your
developers because only then you get the
buy-in from them and already then you
manage this this huge workload and your
role is then to review the design
decisions ensure that they are
consistent overall so this is your key
responsibility and only fourth I would
say bring in your own own design
decisions and your your design
competence because as I said you you
only scale and grow as an organization
when you delegate sufficiently to to the
juniors to the seniors developers to
help them grow
and I haven't seen any degradation in
the quality because at the end you you
have seen all the design decisions
before they are implemented typically
when you do to your child yeah um if you
if you're responsible for the big
picture then in some sense you're also
responsible for implementing the
requirements you know I think you know
having things like you know a certain
required reliability of you know or or
availability of the system or or making
sure that certain performance numbers
are met or just simply being able to
implement the requirements is that also
your job as an architect yes of course
you they are very often that the
ill-at-ease and the non-functional
developmental as well as operational
qualities are in your responsibility to
ensure that they are being taken
seriously that they are follow up on and
then also
[Music]
and shirring at the end of the day that
that somebody measures those a lot ease
and you can then improve and I see that
with the system architect the technical
lead who who really holds those ends
together
let's look at the skills skills of
course here we need to be really perfect
I would say in communication skills
because you communicate a lot as I
mentioned this is your first priority be
good and in writing documentation be
again a role model for the organization
on how to achieve transparency in
InDesign decisions for example come up
with templates come up with coding
guidelines here you need it really good
writing skills and being able to talk to
anybody else in the organization to your
head of Rd to explain the current status
what is going on what are the
consequences to discuss some visionary
things with the product manager so
communication as that's the first skill
so so in this communication just to make
this clear is not just technical it's
also being able to talk to customers or
product managers and again you will
probably have to adapt their language
right okay
analysis analysis skills to really dig
down at at the ground and well you
shouldn't have to dig down always but
when it's necessary and really have them
at the gut feeling for when to dig down
into a problem and when than just to put
the finger into the wound and and feel
what the reaction is now that here I
have a have a good gut feeling rely be
able to rely on you got analysis now the
next one I think is really interesting
it says networking and of course it you
don't talk about Ethernet and tcp/ip
right now if you network of
knowledgeable professionals inside and
outside your company hmm and I believe
us an architect can only then grow and
advance and keep keep up to date when
you keep your network of peers yeah
basically similar to what we did in the
past and when we met at Europe lop yep
and discussed patterns this was for me
and I guess also for you and excellence
excellent chance to meet people with the
same mindset and and ask us and
challenge and exchange your and educate
your yourself yeah going to conferences
is I think really essential for people
like that not just you know not because
it's a bunch of additional weeks of
holidays but it's as you say it's really
about networking looking beyond your own
local problems and and understanding how
the world moves on how the community
things and how new technologies and and
and and and you know approaches
processes and things develop so
conferencing or going to conferences is
I think very useful for that matter
next is the technical leadership and
this is leading without having
disciplinary rights which can be tricky
right it's tricky and challenging you
need to convince our others and here you
again meet your network inside a company
to achieve what you have typically then
no power to really enforce but where you
have your network with your social
skills established and then just get the
job done and this is something a manager
would typically rely on that you have
your network that you are able to
communicate and exchange the ideas and
convince others by get their buy-in for
for solutions win their opinion tap
in some sense marketing right marketing
your ideas to people who should adopt
them and that is more than simple
communication I mean marketing is is is
is giving things a spin so people buy
into it you shouldn't lie but but just
making it very convincing okay
competencies or competencies and
knowledge I would say you should have
been a senior developer for a while Joe
for coming becoming an architect
sometimes I I personally get
applications from from guys from
university that after one year of
developer being at the junior developer
they want to become an architect and
there it's very often there's not the
breadth of of technology and ability to
have strike they haven't seen that many
projects that many successes and
failures that that they can really well
lead big software projects you ain't
seen nothing yet right I'm sorry you
ain't seen nothing yet I think the clash
back in the day is the other demand was
so as an as an architect you should be
able to abstract to as we mentioned
already be really good in writing use
pattern writing as a training for this
yeah by the way another way of of of of
of sharpening your abstraction skills is
language design modeling language design
coming up with metamodels trying to
formalize the domain into things helps
very much in my experience
next thing is something sensitive and
and here we talk about technology and
very often not very often but from time
to time I see architects that are very
much in love with a dedicated technology
and I've tried to apply this hammer to
every screw nail or whatever they find
in front of them and so you should have
a good sense about the various relevant
technologies and they belong cept behind
a technology to really then make a
conscious choice on on the technology
and choose the best suite suited
technology not the choice like
technology as you should be able to look
behind the marketing and hype you know
blah blah and and really see the essence
and really see that Delta between a new
technology and an old technology and see
whether it's just the old crap renamed
or whether there is something new to it
so this this is concluded acknowledged
and competencies with ending having a
broad overview never lose something out
of sight keep the big picture not be in
love with any specific technology be as
broad as possible
I I this is never a failure knowing too
many technologies and concepts that's
them an architect
yeah okay mindset mindset i here i would
put it that way he lost to find
simplicity in complexity so be able to
deal with existing complexity like what
on your predecessor or your previous
prochik just left over
and be able to deal with that complexity
and have an urgent need to structure it
you you love complexity in the sense
that you have the new exciting project
in front of you where you can bring in
your knowledge and your talent to
simplify and structure things yeah so
you don't love technology
sorry you don't love complexity in the
sense that you are one of those
technology sorry you're one of those
complexity junkies because you're the
only one in the project who understands
all this stuff you love it in the sense
that you want to get rid of it you see
it as a challenge to simplify so it's
accessible to others right exactly okay
so I guess that concludes the discussion
about the architect we have more stuff
coming up the technologists the team
lead the requirements engineer the
product manager but I guess that's
that's too much for this episode right
so I guess we we cut here we make a cut
here and continue next time do you want
to add any words of wisdom anything that
concludes this episode before we shut
this down and continue next time yeah I
think I briefly want to summarize what
what the the mindset was so far of a
junior developer and okay developer an
architect so first be be curious about
concepts about technology about
methodology be a pragmatist be find the
simplest solution that could possibly
work be a role model for juniors try to
show and live best practices every day
and motivate others to follow you
okay so then Michael thanks for for
bringing all of this to us and
thanks listeners for listening talk to
you next time bye
[Music]
thanks for listening to software
engineering radio if you want more
information about the podcast and all
the other episodes visit our website and
SE - radio dotnet if you want to support
us you can donate to the SU radio team
via the website or you can advertise for
se radio for example by clicking on the
Digg reddit delicious and slash dog
buttons to contact the team lease an
email to team and Su radio net or if
it's specific to an episode please use
the comments facility on the website so
other people can read and react to your
comments this episode of software
engineering radio as well as all other
episodes are licensed under Creative
Commons license please see the website
for details thanks to Charlie crowd and
the pot safe music Network for the music
used in this show the song is called
Vegas hard rock shuffle
[Music]